<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Slowly Forward – Personal</title><link>https://slowfwd.fr/tags/personal/</link><description>Recent content in Personal on Slowly Forward</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slowfwd.fr/tags/personal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Slowly Forward</title><link>https://slowfwd.fr/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slowfwd.fr/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Hi! This website is, first and foremost, for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I created it as a place to collect and revisit the notes I take on the books I read and the thoughts I have about various topics. If you stumble upon this site and find something useful here, that’s great, but that’s not the primary goal. This is a personal space where I track what I think, how I think, and how my thinking evolves over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some time ago, I realized that my memory, like everyone’s, is imperfect. I forget events, I forget details from books I’ve read, and I even forget insights that once felt important. To some extent, that’s okay. The ideas we absorb often change us subtly, even if we forget where they came from. But I also started to feel that some thoughts are worth preserving, not necessarily the facts themselves, but the reflections and questions they sparked in me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In that sense, this site is a kind of time capsule. A place where I can revisit snapshots of my mind at different points in my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A turning point for me was reading &lt;a href="https://andymatuschak.org/books/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“Why Books Don’t Work” by Andy Matuschak&lt;/a>, which challenged how I thought about reading and memory. That article led me to &lt;em>How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/em> by Sönke Ahrens, where I discovered the Zettelkasten method: a way of building knowledge by writing and linking short, meaningful notes. I tried using tools like Obsidian to implement it. I watched videos, explored best practices, but the truth is, the habit never fully stuck.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I kept reading, but I rarely paused to take good notes. And when I did, I didn’t invest enough time reviewing or refining them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So this website is a new attempt. A more public one. I’m committing to publishing &lt;strong>2 short articles every months&lt;/strong>, drawn from my notes, to help me stay accountable and turn this into a long-lasting habit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If these reflections ever help someone else think differently, that’s the cherry on top.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>