<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Slowly Forward – Entrepreneurship</title><link>https://slowfwd.fr/categories/entrepreneurship/</link><description>Recent content in Entrepreneurship on Slowly Forward</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slowfwd.fr/categories/entrepreneurship/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Starting a Side Hustle with AI: From Childhood Dreams to Modern Experiments</title><link>https://slowfwd.fr/blog/20250731_side_hustle_ai/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slowfwd.fr/blog/20250731_side_hustle_ai/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="AI_startup_journey.png" alt="AI Startup Journey" loading="lazy" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve always been fascinated by the idea of creating my own business. As a child, my dream wasn’t to start a startup or join a big company: it was to invent a teleportation device. I suffered from motion sickness and imagined how wonderful it would be to zap from one place to another without the long, uncomfortable hours in between.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Years later, while studying in Chicago, three friends and I took our first real shot at entrepreneurship. What started as a class assignment grew into something bigger: a startup idea we called HubRoad. The concept was simple but powerful: help students track their job applications in one place, while also providing key resources like interview prep tips and company insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We learned so much in the process: built a business strategy, created a pitch deck, developed a Minimum Viable Product, and coded both the front and back ends ourselves. We even won a prize in our school’s startup competition. At the time, we dreamed big! We wanted to become the next Elon Musk and be rich and famous.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But reality soon caught up with us. We graduated, started our careers, and struggled to keep the project alive while working full-time and living in different cities. Eventually, HubRoad faded away.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2>A Shift in Motivation&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="a-shift-in-motivation">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#a-shift-in-motivation" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Now, several years later, I find myself drawn again to the idea of starting a side hustle. But this time, my motivation is different. I’m not chasing fame or fortune, I want to keep learning. Technology and business strategies evolved so quickly that the best way to stay curious is to experiment firsthand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The biggest difference compared to ten years ago? We now have AI as a creative partner. Instead of staring at a blank page or waiting for inspiration, I can brainstorm with ChatGPT and generate ideas step by step.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, inspired by Anne-Laure Le Cunff’s book Tiny Experiments, I decided to run one myself. I opened ChatGPT and typed:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Can you ask me a set of questions, one after the other, to help me figure out the best side hustle opportunity based on my skills?”&lt;/p>
&lt;h2>The Power of AI Brainstorming&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="the-power-of-ai-brainstorming">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#the-power-of-ai-brainstorming" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The experience surprised me. Instead of spitting out random suggestions, ChatGPT guided me through a reflection process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What skills do I enjoy using?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What motivates me?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What problems do I care about solving?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Step by step, the questions helped me connect dots and learn about my motivations. By the end, I had landed on an idea that felt like me: &lt;strong>a habit-building app for aspiring runners and cyclists that rewards consistency and small wins&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2>What’s Next&lt;span class="hx-absolute -hx-mt-20" id="whats-next">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#whats-next" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>&lt;p>I don’t know yet where this experiment will lead, but that’s exactly the point. This time, the journey matters more than the outcome. Building a side hustle with AI isn’t about chasing the next big thing; it’s about using powerful new tools to learn, create, and grow along the way.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>